Guide to the Theodore Dreiser collection, 1897-1983.
Dreiser, Theodore collection, 1897-1983.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Theodore Dreiser collection, 1897-1983.
4604
Theodore, Dreiser 1871-1945.
24.8 linear ft.
Correspondence, printed material, photographs, interviews, speeches, research notes, clippings, microfilms, an audiotape, manuscripts, phonograph records, and a film.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Consists mainly of letters by, to, or about Theodore Dreiser, as well as printed material, photographs, interviews and speeches of Dreiser and research notes of Dreiser scholar Robert Elias.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
American author of the naturalist school, who began as a journalist and was also active in support of communism.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Consists mainly of letters by, to, or about Theodore Dreiser, as well as printed material, photographs, interviews and speeches of Dreiser, research notes of Dreiser scholar Robert Elias, clippings, microfilms, 1 audio tape, and 2 vols. of bound manuscripts. Includes copies of Dreiser's extensive correspondence with H.L. Mencken, and originals of many letters from Mencken to Elias; printed articles and stories which Dreiser published in The Bookman, Daily Worker, The Delineator, Famous Stories, Forum, The New York Herald Tribune, The New York Times, Pravda, Tass, and Vanity Fair, including articles in support of communism and organized labor; manuscripts of Dreiser's works The Bulwark and My Creator, and the outline of a play, Revolt; and correspondence (mainly typed copies of letters) with other writers. Includes phonograph records, and a short film of Dreiser in Westchester County, 1938.
Correspondents include Sherwood Anderson, Argus Book Shop, Louise Campbell, Sergei Dinamov, George Douglas, Helen Dreiser, James T. Farrell, Charles Fort, Frank Harris, Arthur Garfield Hays, Maude Wood Henry, Harold Hersey, John Huth, Alfred A. Knopf, William C. Lengel, Donald P. McCord, Esther McCoy, H.L. Mencken, Albert Mordell, George Jean Nathan, Grant Richards, Franklin Delano Roosevelt, Simon & Schuster, Upton Sinclair, Thelma Cudlipp Whitman, and Huan Wilson.
The collection also includes one 7" reel sound recording (tape) and two CD's (one master and one use copy) of radio broadcasts. Also included is a videotape of Dreiser and Harriet Bissell at Mt. Kisco, N.Y., in May 1938, filmed by Robert Elias.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Dreiser, Theodore, 1871-1945.; Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941.; Campbell, Louise Grace, 1907-; Dinamov, Sergei.; Dos Passos, John, 1896-1970.; Douglas, George.; Dreiser, Helen Patges, d. 1955.; Dreiser, Theodore, 1871-1945.; Dreiser, Theodore, 1871-1945.; Elias, Robert H.; Harris, Frank, 1855-1931.; Hays, Arthur Garfield, 1881-1954.; Henry, Maude Wood.; Hersey, Harold Brainerd, 1893-; Huth, John F.; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984.; Lengel, William C. (William Charles), 1888-1965.; McCord, Donald P.; McCoy, Esther.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Mordell, Albert, 1885-; Nathan, George Jean, 1882-1958.; Richards, Grant, 1872-1948.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968.; Whitman, Thelma Cudlipp, 1892-; Wilson, Huan.; Argus Book Shop.; Simon and Schuster, Inc.
Subjects:
American literature--20th century.; American periodicals.; Modernism (Literature).; Censorship--United States.; Domestic relations--United States.; Authors, American.; Journalists--United States.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Portraits.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Related collection, including originals of Dreiser's letters, at: University of Pennsylvania.
Sound recordings are cataloged individually.
Bound manuscripts, which include two volumes of correspondence and clippings concerning the suppression of Dreiser's novel "The Genius" under censorship pressure from the New York Society for the Suppression of Vice, are cataloged individually.
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Printed material by Dreiser, printed material by other writers, and Dreiser's letters to others arranged in chronological order; letters and manuscripts by others arranged alphabetically by author; letters received by Elias arranged in chronological order.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Manuscripts
  - Undated, 1903-1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932-1945 (Box 2)
- Series II. Printed materials
  - 1892-Jul. 1898 (Box 3)
  - Aug. 1898-Apr. 1899 (Box 4)
  - May-Dec. 1899 (Box 5)
  - 1900-Nov. 1901 (Box 6)
  - Dec. 1901-May 1905 (Box 7)
  - Jun. 1905-1912 (Box 8)
  - 1913-1914 (Box 9)
  - 1915-1919 (Box 10)
  - 1920-1923 (Box 11)
  - 1924-1925 (Box 12)
  - 1926-1927 (Box 13)
  - 1928 (Box 14)
  - 1929 (Box 15)
  - This Madness, 1929 (Box 16)
  - 1930-1933 (Box 17)
  - Jan.-Jun. 1934 (Box 18)
  - Jul.-Dec. 1934 (Box 19)
  - 1935-1936 (Box 20)
  - 1937 (Box 21)
  - 1938 (Box 22)
  - 1939-1943 (Box 23)
  - 1944 (Box 24)
  - 1945-1959 (Box 25)
- Series III. Printed materials by others
  - 1901-1914 (Box 26)
  - 1915-1927 (Box 27)
  - 1928-1932 (Box 28)
  - 1933-1945 (Box 29)
  - 1946 (Box 30)
  - 1947-1969 (Box 31)
  - 1970- (Box 32)
- Series IV. Outgoing correspondence
  - Undated, 1897-1909 (Box 33)
  - 1910-1911 (Box 34)
  - 1912-1913 (Box 35)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 36)
  - 1916-1917 (Box 37)
  - 1918-1919 (Box 38)
  - 1920 (Box 39)
  - 1921-1922 (Box 40)
  - 1923-1924 (Box 41)
  - 1925 (Box 42)
  - 1926-1927 (Box 43)
  - 1928-1929 (Box 44)
  - 1930-1931 (Box 45)
  - Jan.-Aug. 1932 (Box 46)
  - Sept.-Dec. 1932 (Box 47)
  - Jan.-May 1 933 (Box 48)
  - Jun.-Dec. 1933 (Box 49)
  - 1934 (Box 50)
  - 1935 (Box 51)
  - 1936-1937 (Box 52)
  - 1938-May 1939 (Box 53)
  - Jun. 1939-Sept. 1940 (Box 54)
  - Oct. 1940-1942 (Box 55)
  - 1943-1945 (Box 56)
- Series V. Correspondence and manuscripts by others
  - A-Douf (Box 57)
  - Doug-Dr Douglas (Box 58)
  - Douglas, George
    - Manuscripts (Box 59)
    - Memorabilia 1 (Box 60)
    - Memorabilia 2 (Box 61)
    - Memorabilia 3 (Box 62)
  - Elias, Robert
    - Ds-E (Box 63)
    - Outgoing Correspondence and Manuscripts (Box 64)
    - Notes 1 (Box 65)
    - Notes 2 (Box 66)
  - Elias, Robert, incoming correspondence
    - Undated, 1937-1944 (Box 67)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 68)
    - 1947-1952 (Box 69)
    - 1953-1959 (Box 70)
    - F-Hec (Box 71)
    - Hed-Hi (Box 72)
    - Hj-K (Box 73)
    - L-Mem (Box 74)
    - Men-Nim (Box 75)
    - Nin-Q (Box 76)
    - R-T (Box 77)
    - U-Z (Box 78)
- Series VI. Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 79)
- Series VII. Clippings
  - Reviews of Dreiser's Works (Box 80)
  - A-Z (Box 81)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 82)
  - Elias, Robert, Theodore Dreiser: Apostle of Nature (Box 83)
  - Elias, Robert, Letters of Theodore Dreiser (Box 84)
- Series VIII. Dreiseriana
  - Dreiseriana (Box 85)
- Series IX. Printed materials (oversize)
  - Printed materials (Box 86)
- Series X. Media
  - DVD reformatted from 16mm film of Theodore Dreiser at Irok (box contains film, as well), DVD-696 (Box 87)
  - Video of Dreiser and Harriet Bissell at Mt. Kisco, N.Y., May 1938, V-1116
  - CD's of radio broadcasts, "What can our children believe?", Nov. 18, 1936, CD-1&2
  - 7" reel sound recording (tape) of radio broadcasts, tr-7887